Guide to the Olin Sewall Pettingill, Jr. papers, [ca. 1895-1990].
Pettingill, Olin Sewall, Jr. Papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Olin Sewall Pettingill, Jr. papers, [ca. 1895-1990].
4047
Pettingill, Olin Sewall, Jr.,
13.4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, research material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Professional correspondence; photographic negatives of birds; notes and rsearch materials relating to his book.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Olin Sewall Pettingill was born in Maine on October 30, 1907. He received a Ph.D. from Cornell University in 1933. He was a college instructor of biology and ornithology and in 1960 was appointed Director of the Laboratory of Ornithology at Cornell University, a post he held until his retirement in 1973. For 35 summers, beginning in 1938, he taught ornithology at the University of Michigan Biological Station. He was secretary, vice-president, and president of the Wilson Ornithological Society and secretary of the American Ornithologists' Union, of which he was elected a life fellow in 1947. He was elected a Director of the National Audubon Society in 1955. He edited several books and magazines on ornithology. In 1974 he received the Arthur A. Allen Award from Cornell University for distinguished service to ornithology.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Professional correspondence; photographic negatives coded by species of bird; notes of places to see birds in each of the states in preparation for his book; some manuscript material; correspondence about the book THE BIRD WATCHER'S AMERICA, edited by Pettingill; vita, 1990; bibliography; and articles. Special projects include field work in the Galapagos Islands, Grand Manan, and Mexico, and research on the whooping crane. Major correspondents include W.J. Breckinridge, Maurice Brooks, Thornton W. Burgess, John Henry Dick, Harvey I. Fisher, Alfred O. Gross, George Hall, Margaret Morse Nice, Roger Tory Peterson, Maurice Rumboll, George M. Sutton (relating to a memorial), Gustav A. Swanson, and William Zimmerman.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Pettingill, Olin Sewall, Jr., 1907-; Breckinridge, W. J.; Brooks, Maurice.; Burgess, Thornton W. (Thornton Waldo), 1874-1965.; Dick, John Henry, 1919-; Fisher, Harvey I.; Gross, Alfred Otto, 1883-1970.; Hall, George.; Nice, Margaret Morse, 1993-1974.; Peterson, Roger Tory, 1908-; Pettingill, Olin Sewall, Jr.; Rumboll, Maurice.; Sutton, George Miksch, 1898-; Swanson, Gustav Adolf, 1910-; Zimmerman, William.
Subjects:
Ornithology -- Study and teaching.; Ornithology -- Field work.; Birds -- Research.; Scientific expeditions -- Argentina.; Scientific expeditions -- Galapagos Islands.; Scientific expeditions -- Mexico.; Whooping crane.; Ornithologists.; College teachers.
Form and Genre Terms:
Negatives.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Research for Field Guides
  - Alabama - Illinois
    - Alabama, 1949-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alaska (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Arizona(1), 1947-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Arizona(2) - Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Proofs for book
    - Arkansas, 1947-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Arkansas(2) - Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - California, 1947-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - California(2) - Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Also includes a 1966 California Map
    - Colorado, 1947-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Colorado(2) - Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Connecticut, 1947-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Deleware, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Florida, 1947-1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Georgia, 1947-1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Hawaii, 1955-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Idaho, 1947-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Idaho(2) - Manuscript (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Also includes a 1976-1977 Idaho Map
    - Illinois, 1947-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Indiana - Montana
    - Indiana, 1947-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Iowa, 1947-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Iowa(2) - Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Includes a 1976-1977 Iowa roadmap and maps for De Soto National Wildlife Refuge
    - Kansas, 1947-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Kansas(2)-Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Includes a 1969-1970 Flint Hills National Wildlife Refuge brochure
    - Kentucky, 1946-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Louisiana, 1947-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Louisiana(2) - Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes a 1979-1980 Louisiana road map
    - Maine, 1947-1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Maryland, 1947-1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Massachusetts, 1947-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Michigan, 1947-1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Minnesota, 1947-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Minnesota(2) - Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Includes 1976 and 1977-1978 Minnesota road maps, Hennepin map and Camping in Minnesota brochure
    - Mississippi, 1947-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Missouri, 1947-1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Missouri(2) - Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Montana, 1947-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Montana(2) - Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Includes a 1975 Montana road map
  - Nebraska - Oregon
    - Nebraska, 1947-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Nebraska(2) - Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Includes a 1976 Nebraska road map
    - Nevada, 1947-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Nevada(2) - Manuscript, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - New Hampshire, 1947-1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - New Jersey, 1947-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - New Mexico, 1947-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - New Mexico(2) - Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Includes a New Mexico road map
    - New York, 1947-1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - New York City Area, 1956-1976 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - North Carolina, 1947-1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - North Dakota, 1947-1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - North Dakota(2) - Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Includes a 1975 North Dakota road map
    - Ohio, 1947-1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Oklahoma, 1947-1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Okalahoma(2) - Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Includes a 1967, 1977 and an undated (with notations) Oklahoma City Street Map and a 1977 Oklahoma road map
    - Oregon, 1947-1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Oregon(2)- For column in Audubon Magazine, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Oregon(3)- Manuscript (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Includes a 1979 Oregon Road map and 1978 lists of state parks
  - Pennsylvania - Washington
    - Pennsylvania, 1946-1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Rhode Island, 1946-1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - South Carolina, 1947-1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - South Dakota, 1947-1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - South Dakota(2) - Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Includes a 1977-1978 South Dakota road map
    - Tennessee, 1947-1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Texas, 1947-1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Texas(2) Second Edition, 1962-1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Texas(3) - Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Includes a 1977-1978 Oklahoma Texas road map and a 1973 Texas road map
    - Utah, 1949-1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Utah(2) - Zion National Park, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Utah(3) - Manuscript, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes a 1979 Utah road map
    - Vermont, 1947-1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Virginia, 1947-1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Washington, 1947-1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Washington(2) - Manuscript, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - West Virginia - Wyoming
    - West Viginia, 1947-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Wisconsin, 1947-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Wyoming(1), 1949-1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Wyoming(2), 1952-1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Wyoming(3) - Manuscript, c.1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Proofs for Book and Wyoming road maps
- Series II. Correspondence
  - A-G
    - A - Correspondence, 1949-1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Argentine Field Trip, 1964-1969 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - B - Correspondence, 1931-1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - B - Correspondence, 1962-1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Breckenridge, 1947-1984 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Brooks, 1947-1966 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Burgess, Thornton, W., 1928-1984 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - C - Correspondence, 1930-1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - C - Correspondence, 1974-1986 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - D - Correspondence, 1931-1987 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Dick, John Henry, 1964-1975 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - E - Correspondence, 1932-1985 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - F - Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Fisher, Harvey I., 1964-1982 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - G- Correspondence, 1934-1974 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - G - Correspondence, 1975-1988 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Gallapagos Islands, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Grand Manan, 1932-1936 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Gross, 1928-1971 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - H-Q
    - H - Correspondence, 1931-1968 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - H - Correpondence, 1970-1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Hall, George (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - J - Correspondence, 1936-1988 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - K - Correspondence, 1928-1986 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - L - Correspondence, 1932-1949 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - L - Correspondence, 1950-1986 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - M - Correspondence, 1930-1949 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - M - Correspondence, 1950-1988 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Mc - Correspondence (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Mexican Expedition, 1940-1941 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - N - Correspondence, 1930-1981 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Nice, Margaret, 1938-1967 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - O - Correspondence, 1936-1983 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - P - Correspondence, 1931-1964 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - P - Correspondence, 1965-1988 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Peterson, Roger Tory (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Q - Correspondence, 1953-1958 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - R-Z
    - R - Correspondence, 1931-1958 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - R - Correspondence, 1960-1985 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Rumball, Maurice, 1974-1984 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - S - Correspondence, 1931-1959 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - S - Correspondence, 1960-1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Sutton, George, 1983-1986 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Relating to Sutton's memorial and Pettingill's forward to Sutton's last book, "Birds Worth Knowing"
    - Swanson, Gustav, 1937-1986 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - T - Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - U - Correspondence, 1942-1983 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - V - Correspondence, 1933-1972 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - W - Correspondence, 1933-1985 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Whooping Crane, 1945-1979 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Wilson Ornithological Club, 1938-1993 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - X,Y,Z - Correspondence, 1944-1984 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Zimmerman, William, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Series III. Biographic Materials
  - Bibliography, Biography and Memorials, 1988-1990 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - School diplomas, degrees and other certificates, 1897-1974 (Box 13)
    For Pettingill, Olin S.; Rice, Eleanor; Norris, Luther; Pettingill, Marion G.; Bradbury, Marion
  - Olin Sewall Pettingill, MD - American College of Physicians - Fellow Certificate, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - School diplomas, degrees and other certificates, 1895-1940 (Folder 2)
    For Pettingill, Olin S. and Pettingill, Sewall
  - Pettingill Christmas Card Drawings (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Sewall Pettingill - Stationery, c.1901-1909 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Series IV. Photographs
  - Negatives - Pettingill's Catalog of Bird Negatives. Note: there is a species index for this in Box 6-1.
    - Negatives #100-1411, 1929-1940 (Box 6-1)
      Negatives of birds in individual envelopes. Bird name, geographic location and date given. Some include printed photographs.
      There is an index for the bird catalog in Box 6-1.
    - Negatives #1500-4312, 1931-1945 (Box 6-2)
    - Negatives #4400-5115, 1930-1942 (Box 7-1)
    - Negatives #5201-6345, 1931-1936 (Box 7-2)
    - Negatives #6400-8311, 1933-1941 (Box 15-1)
    - Negatives #8400-10218, 1929-1948 (Box 15-2)
    - Negatives #10300-14519, -1944 (Box 16-1)
    - Negatives #14520-16308. Also includes #3-112, misc bird photos and photos of mammals not included in index, c.1929-1949 (Box 16-2)
      This box includes oversize negatives from Box 6-1 and 7-1
  - Prints - Birds taken by Pettingill
    - 22 16"x20" matted photographs for exhibition (Box 11)
      Includes bird names
    - 2 14"x15" matted photographs (Box 11)
    - 1 13"x16" matted photograph (Box 11)
    - Loose Photographs (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Information on Olin S. Pettingill for Exhibition (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 5 13.5"x18" hand colored black and white prints (Box 13)
    - Penguins and Seagull (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - Hoary Redpoll on Nest (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - American Woodcock - Ithaca, NY (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Bonaparte's Gull Chick (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Bonaparte's Gull - Hudson Bay (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Stilt Sandpiper (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Willow Ptarmigan, Strutting (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - King Penguin - Falklands (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Prints - Birds taken by others
    - Eagle by Fred Kent Truslow (Box 11)
      Signed by photographer
  - Prints - Ornithologists and Ornithology Organizations
    - Great Lakes Ornithological Club, 1909 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Allen, Arthur A. (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Breckenridge, Walter J., c.1930 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Chapman, Fran, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Gross, Alfred, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      Bowdoin College Professor
    - Peterson, P.T. (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Pettingills, Mr. and Mrs. (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Roberts, Thomas S., 1939 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Sutton, George Miksch (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Swanson, Gustav, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Van Tyne, Josselyn and Gould, Lawrence McKinley (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Allen Award Dinner, October 1970 (Folder 1)
      Wentmore, Alexander and Treman, Margo
    - University of Michigan Biological Station, 1928 (Folder 2)
    - University of Michigan Biological Station, 1929 (Folder 2)
    - 3 photographs of the 96th Convention of Psi Upsilon Frat, 1929 (Folder 2)
    - American Ornithologist Union, 1940, 1941, 1954, 1957 (Folder 2)
    - Joint Meeting of the American Trudeau Society - Tuberculosis Sanitoring Conference (Folder 2)
- Series V. Illustration Collection
  - Pamphlets and Bound Materials
    - Bird and Wildlife Illustrations - Series and Pamphlets (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Magazines, 1935-1987 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      Includes a 1936 The Sportsman with an article by Pettingill
    - Bird and Outdoor Illustrations - Series and Pamphlets, c.1949-1952 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Includes a series of reproductions of "Exoctic Birds" by John Gould
    - Pamphlets and booklets relating to birding and other wildlife (Box 14, Folder 23)
      Includes a booklet entitled "History of Birds: For the Use of Children" from 1843
  - Loose Illustrations
    - Bird Illustrations - Prints from the Riegel Portfolio of Carolina Birds, 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Reproductions of Arthur Singer paintings
    - Bird Illustrations, 1936-1984 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Bird Illustrations - Oversize (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Posters (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Bird Illustrations (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Monographs, Clippings and Postcards of Birds (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Article about Olin Pettingill, 1948 (Folder 1)
      Includes reproductions of his photographs
    - Posters (Folder 2)
      Uruguay and Walt Disney's "Water Birds"
- Series VI. Bird Related Ephemera
  - Lecture Flyers and Sheet Music (Box 13, Folder 5)